[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software hi this is Stefan silica
for software engineering radio today I'm
sitting down with Michael Nygaard
Michael is widely known for his
presentations and writings about
software and system architecture as a
contributor to the books beautiful
architecture and 97 things every
architect should know and probably most
notably first phenomenal book release it
which was the topic of episode 134 of
this podcast these days Michael works as
an architect at cockney tech our topic
today is closer in practice and we'll
take a look at how this Lisp like
language is being used in real-world
projects so Mike welcome to the show I'm
really happy to have you with us here
most of our listeners know you from your
work in the areas of architecture and
stability patterns and resilient systems
but today we're gonna talk about closure
can you tell us a little bit about how
you got into the closure world and what
interested you absolutely it started
around 2007 I think I had been working
in Java for a long time since 1995 and
was like a lot of people I think
beginning to feel a little stagnant with
Java the language but reluctant to
discard Java the ecosystem and all the
libraries and the vast amounts of code
that were available so I started looking
at some of the jvm languages and first I
went to Scala I was attracted by the
parser Combinator library in Scala and
it was a completely new way of writing
parsers to me so I moved into Scala and
worked in that for about two years
when I saw Stu holloway give a
presentation on closure and at that time
it absolutely floored me you know like
many people I'd been exposed to Lisp
before
and sort of had this feeling that you
know it was a nice academic thing but
not something a programmer used in the
real world and Stu showed me that indeed
it could be a real-world language and I
pretty much immediately dropped Scala
and started moving into closure ok maybe
before we start talking about in more
detail about about closure what was it
what was it actually that frustrated he
with with Scala because I know many
people like Scala and I'm very happy
with the language it wasn't so much that
I was frustrated with Scala although I
certainly did feel like I had not
mastered the type system well enough to
make it work for me I was working for it
but it was more that the clean
expression of ideas in closure appealed
to me so it was a move toward not a move
away mm-hmm makes sense so can you give
those of our listeners who know nothing
about closure a brief introduction
certainly as I mentioned it's a lisp so
it's in the family of parentheses
delimited languages rather than curly
brace delimited that's the most obvious
thing on the surface what it really
provides under the covers though is
language and a library that strongly
favors immutable data structures and
very precise control over how you manage
your state and so it makes a nice
language for building multi-threaded
applications and in general there are
all kinds of concerns about mutation
that you run into in a typical program
that you simply don't have with closure
if I have a map I can rely on changing
that map in whatever way necessary
because I'm only changing successive
copies of the map and whoever gave me
the original map can continue using
their copy of it and so forth and so it
really makes a lot of things simpler to
implement that way ok talk a bit about
how culture achieves efficiency with
that without restriction yeah definitely
the first thing that you would think of
with that amount of copying going on is
oh my god the garbage collector you
you're going to be creating a lot of
garbage and that's partially true but
closures data structures are based on
what people call persistent data
structures not persistent than in the
sense of being persisted to disk but the
idea that there's a lot of structural
sharing that goes on so when I have
something that claims to be a list it's
not strictly implemented as a linked
list it's actually implemented as a
fairly wide tree and when I create a
copy of the list with a new item cons
bond to the end or appended to the end I
get back a new tree root with many
pointers into the old portions of the
prior tree so by the time we reach the
leaf nodes almost all of the pointers
are the same and they're pointing to the
same items in memory this relieves a lot
of the garbage collector pressure and
makes a lot of these list operations
very fast so I think you've mentioned to
two differences between a closure and
other languages one is that it's
actually a lot full of parents the other
one is that it actually has these
immutable data structures if you were to
name I don't know one or two other key
features that you consider that makes
the language really different from other
languages what would those be I would
have to name the transactional memory so
in Java when you're doing
multi-threading you use a lot of locks
and so we're all familiar with wait and
notify in closure we don't really use
those instead we control the point in
time at which we change something and
we're typically only changing a
reference to a thing so closure includes
a couple of constructs called refs and
atoms an atom is you can think of it as
a pointer to a value I can dereference
that atom and get the real value out the
values then immutable I can also change
the atom by executing a function on it
so we have an operation called swap that
calls a function with the current value
of the atom and whatever the function
returns becomes the new value of the
atom this is how most applications
manage their state is with an atom
there are also refs which have this
aspect of being transactional I can
start a block called do sink everything
in that block either happens or does not
happen so it acts much like a database
transaction and within the block I can
access a bunch of refs and I can modify
a bunch of refs they're all going to
give me back the consistent value that
they had at the beginning and all of the
changes get applied together so it
sounds a bit as if there's a lot of very
complex machinery hidden underneath that
is exposed to give you a very simplified
programming model is that a fair summary
of the language from your point of view
it's definitely fair to say that we have
a simplified programming model I can't
actually speak to how complex the
machinery is underneath
I suspect that somewhere it bottoms out
in Java locks and monitors just like
everything else in the JVM but it's not
something that I've ever had to
encounter as a user of closure
mm-hm in the sense of completeness you
mentioned that you've got attracted to
it or one of its attractions was that it
runs in the JVM but it also runs on the
on the JavaScript platform by now right
are you familiar with that one as well
do you use it as well I have begun using
closure script mainly because I've been
impressed with some of the amazing
front-end work that colleagues of mine
have done I'm not myself a JavaScript
programmer so I can't speak to that
aspect of it too much I will say that
closure and closure script our best
regarded as sibling languages it's not
precisely the same language on both
platforms mm-hmm okay so one of the
things that I find interesting and that
we talked about when we plant as episode
was that there are a lot of introductory
podcasts and tutorials and articles on
closure and there is a lot of very very
low-level detail stuff about intricate
details but there is not a lot of
practical advise about how to go about
building programs so this is the topic
that we agreed we wanted we want to dive
into more
details so can you talk a bit about how
you go about actually building a program
maybe first of all starting with with a
toolset if you use closure to use your
typical Eclipse IDE or you an e makes
person is the toolset different or the
same to the one that you used when you
were doing Java programming I'm an e max
person and so I tend to use Emacs for
this I did not use Emacs when I was a
Java developer I did use Eclipse then I
know the Eclipse closure plug-in works
well I've I used it for six months late
last year and I also know that the
IntelliJ plug-in works exceedingly well
and I would say that those who are in a
race for functionality and users as for
myself I generally start with eclipse
and line again which is sort of a
automation tool in the closure space
performs a lot of the same functions
that you would find in an ant or maven
type of build so a simple line again
file or project created from a template
that's enough to get me started and
pretty much the first thing I do is run
a repple a read evaluate print loop and
this is the probably the biggest
difference in day-to-day workflow for a
closure developer versus Java developer
we get this interactive environment
where we can submit bits of code
function calls and definitions to the
running closure environment that also
has all of our application code and so
it's very common to see some one sort of
iterating on an idea in the repple you
know I'll start by capturing a data
structure or a piece of data that's
going to be flowing around my program
and I'll just look at it and you know
find out what type it is
and what operations I can do on it and I
start putting together pieces of a
function kind of you know one bit at a
time looking at the output as I go
building up a more interesting set of
operations and then I move that code
into source files put proper function
definitions on it fix all my awful
temporary variable names and really make
it something that's going to be part of
my application so in terms of workflow
it's very iterative and I tend not to do
as much from unit tests as I would in a
straight-up java application where i
write tests it's more to nail down
behavior that i want to last rather than
the sometimes more exploratory tests
that you would do in a java project so
the fair to say that the repple takes
the place of a lot of the tests that you
were that you were using when we were
doing TDD it definitely does and I would
say not only the tests but it also in
large part takes the place of a debugger
it's pretty seldom that I need to walk
through code one statement at a time
most of the time if I want to debug
something I'll actually run the
production code in the real application
and capture one of the values into a
variable which I can then inspect from
the repple so this is a common debugging
technique where you put a little def
statement inside of some function say
we're building a web app I put a def
statement inside a request handler that
captures the state of the request at
that time then I go to the repple and
look at what that state actually is so I
don't need a debugger with a variable
inspector because I have the repple to
look at all my variables so let's talk
about those parts that make up a
scenario you have your running
application which is still something
running a server socket on the JVM
somewhere yeah and there's the repple
and there is your Emacs or eclipse isn't
really that different at that regard
right what's which what runs where yeah
that's a totally fair question the
repple is just a way of interacting with
the closure environment that your
application is running in on the JVM so
I have one process which is you know
running we typically use jetty or neti
it's running
that it's got the application code and
the repple is executing in that JVM then
from Emacs or from eclipse you would
connect to the repple over a socket so
it listens on the network okay so it's
actually two parts it's the IDE that you
happen to use and the running
application that offers you the
opportunity to interact with it
dynamically or interactively right
that's right it's back-channel that's
right
okay the repple it actually has a
network protocol so that many of the
different IDE s all have a common way of
interacting with the closure environment
so hopefully we'll we'll see better and
better tools because they can all build
on the same substrate inside the closure
process mm-hmm so what you described is
this interactive process that you're
following and that sounds like really
the exploratory part of the whole thing
where you find out what it is that you
actually want to build and try out new
ideas and play around with what you have
and maybe find the solution to a problem
within your existing system but how does
that relate to design how do you go
about designing I don't know a domain
that's more than then trivial if you
have I don't know you have a I don't
know 25 you would have 25 classes in
your domain model in your bounded
context using all that terminology from
the old world
what's the analogy in the closure world
I find that some of the analogy or some
of the approaches carry over directly
and some do not
so I spent a long time as a NOAA
programmer and that was the lens through
which I viewed all problems in the whole
world
and in that space the layered
architecture is sort of the standard
approach right I would say when I
started moving to closure I had a number
of conversations that sort of said wait
a minute
we're going back to data flow aren't we
going to have all these horrible
coupling problems that led to the
creation of oo in the first place are we
just recapitulating history from the 80s
and
say that is a risk if you don't impose
some structure on your system so we
don't yet have a lot of shall we say
application frameworks in the closure
space every application sort of starts
from a blank slate if you're doing a web
application you have you know you're
going to have routes and you know you're
going to have a connector to HTTP and
beyond that it's up to you to actually
decide what the structure will be so in
doing that I do go back to the notion of
a bounded context because I I truly
don't want my entire application
becoming this interlinked set of
functions that all know each other's
data structures and the precise inputs
and outputs I create an area and say
within this area all the functions are
allowed to know that we're using a map
with these keys in it and that you know
the value of this key is going to be a
vector of pairs or something along those
lines but on the outside of that no
one's allowed to know the structure
there will be simple functions for
looking up and creating instances of
whatever my data is and there will be
functions for manipulating it and if
that starts to sound like objects there
there's a reason for that those those oo
concepts of encapsulation and
information hiding are still important
as a means of structuring your program
what we don't typically do though is
take the individual pieces of data and
wrap them up in objects and so we have
this idea that says use objects to
structure your system but don't hide
your data behind this confined namespace
so maybe I don't think we actually
mentioned this I think it's important to
know that closure is a dynamically typed
language so you do not have to create
an explicit type for first of course you
don't have to do that in a statically
typed language either but it's sort of
not common to to do that in the in the
closure world right you'd end up just
using data as opposed to creating new
data structures all the time is that a
fair way to express it that is a fair
way I might also say closure provides a
good set of data structures out of the
box lists as you would expect in any
Lisp
but also vectors maps and sets and it
provides great functions in the library
for manipulating those things so in a
sense if you start to hide those behind
an object boundary you're tying an arm
behind your back because you're giving
up all of those built-in functions
closure does have I would say optional
object oriented structures but you get
them a la carte so I can get polymorphic
dispatch using something called multi
methods so take all the examples of I
don't know a bank accounts or shapes or
dogs or whatever whatever you like from
the text books all of those basically
just do dispatch on their first argument
meaning you know look up the class of
the first argument and find the
appropriate implementation for that I
can get exactly that with multi methods
but I don't have to hide it behind a
class boundary so I can have a multi
method with a dispatch function that
says I expect a map and I'm going to
look for a key in the map called type or
classifier and then I'm going to have
method implementations that each receive
the call if their value matches the
value that the dispatch function created
I'm not as great a communicator as Stu
Holloway so I'm making this sound much
more complicated than it really is the
reason I call it optional features
though is because I don't have to use
multi methods unless I choose to and I
can use them point wise in different
areas of my application
so one of the things that I that I find
is a frequent topic of discussion in
this area and let me let me put that to
you as a question is that maybe all this
simplicity is just an illusion because
it just seems simple because you're not
doing anything real with it yeah right
you're just you're just playing around
of course it's simple once you started
hitting the real problems you'll end up
building something that's just as
complicated as the stuff we have in
other languages or other environments as
well do you find that to be true or is
that is this simplicity preserved over
the course of a project's lifecycle and
what is actually the typical project
lifecycle of a project you do with
closure in terms of simplicity of course
you know you can optimize a language for
making code samples on presentation
slides look nice but I find that it it
is something that you can carry through
as you build an application but it does
require some discipline in order to do
it and so a very common pattern for me
in implementing something is I'll do it
the first time realize that I've
intertwined several different issues and
created special cases all over the place
start pulling it apart into constituent
functions that are decomposed orthogonal
ii-in and each generalized and then I
realize that you know a quarter or half
of those functions I created are just
duplicates of library functions and and
so they'll kind of you know cancel each
other out and factor out to nothing and
you know the longer I work on a piece of
my application the smaller it gets and
the more general it gets so in that
sense simplicity is I think easy to
achieve in closure but it's not it's not
automatic and part of what it really
makes me do is appreciate the incredible
amount of thought and and careful
planning and pure good taste that rich
exhibited in creating the library the
second part is ridicu being the creator
of closure
the the second aspect of maintaining
simplicity is that we just have smaller
code bases to deal with so we've we've
got I think some pretty sophisticated
applications running now I'm just
wrapping up a project that is an
interactive development environment for
games so it manages all the assets of
building a game gives you graphical 3d
editors running at 60 frames per second
rendered via OpenGL all of this using
Java FX and it's got an extensibility
model that will allow game developers on
a project to extend the tool from within
the tool in a very sort of Emax like way
all of that is still less than 40,000
lines of code and so just when things
are smaller they can be easier to
replace or rewrite or refactor in pretty
aggressive ways so that's another way
that you can iteratively achieve
simplicity even if it's not necessarily
there in your first implementation which
dare making a guess on how big that
copays would be if you'd build it in
something else well I don't have to
guess because the previous iteration was
built on top of eclipse so that the
system were replacing was deployed and
and worked and that was about a quarter
million lines of Java code in addition
to eclipse itself the new version is not
based on Eclipse so it has to provide
you know all the things like maintaining
a menu structure and knowing who to
target with a cut copy paste command
those sorts of plumbing issues that
Eclipse handles for you and that all
fits in the 40,000 lines and do you
think that if somebody were to maintain
that code base could they take over from
you or does it have to be something like
Mike Nygaard who has to maintain that
code base what's the level of skill
required to work with that kind of code
I have a data point on that which is
that the lead davell
on this from the client side started his
closure work in January of this year so
2015 at this point by April he was
making very meaningful contributions and
now is completely poised to take over
maintenance in the future so he's he's
not what I would call an average
developer he is a fantastic developer
with tons of experience and picked up on
things very very quickly so your mileage
may vary but it's certainly possible to
get people to adopt the applications and
and run forward with them in fact
they've they've added someone to the
team who I think took less than a month
to go from Java Enterprise background to
working on closure in this graphical
environment mm-hm okay very impressive
so if I think if this is a kind of I
think for most of our for a lot of our
listeners this is kind of a unusual
scenario there's game development firm
yes interesting unusual for me as well
so what let's talk about the stuff that
about the boring stuff that most people
including me pay their bills with you
know these typical database back
business applications that maintain some
system record or some commerce process
is that something that you that you
think is is it candidate to be built
closure as well yeah I definitely have
to say yes because the majority of our
work is that as well I think they're
they're pretty good fits for closure and
so let's talk primarily web applications
one of the big every are probably
everything is a web application these
days just just about yeah even desktop
apps are really web apps in a container
of some kind the custom browser yeah so
one of the things that we always deal
with in web applications is sort of the
the layering into domain model and
persistence layer and or mapping and and
so on and I would say we we would tend
to approach things in a pretty similar
way where we're going to have functions
that are each responsible for dealing
with some some concepts in the domain
but instead of having those fund
call through two objects which are
supplied by a mapping layer what we tend
to do is separate our application or the
the flow of a request into query logic
transaction so most closure web stacks
ring and pedestal and so on are based on
an idea of middleware where a request
arrives at the server and then it goes
through some number of stages of
processing before it finally reaches a
handler that's going to emit HTML or
JSON or whatever and those pieces of
middleware can check for authentication
check for validity of the request and
they can attach more state to this
request map as it passes through the
pipeline so the request map has all of
your HTTP headers your request body
everything like that is all in there and
we may have a middleware that says I
expect the request body to be JSON
formatted so I'm going to parse the JSON
string and then reattach that as
parameter and then call the next
middleware function with the modified
map so middleware in this sense is more
of the more direct terminology from Ruby
or from rails right yeah that's to be of
having it's not the middleware in the
traditional Enterprise middleware sense
it's more a little piece of a little
function that enriches or modifies
mutates the request as it flows through
the processing pipeline is that correct
yes that's exactly correct thank you for
that clarification I was not thrilled
with the choice of middleware for those
functions there the name middleware but
yes it's up for some reason that
happened probably somebody didn't have
the negative connotation with middle
married some other people have so no no
that that was helpful so we would put
more middleware in the pipeline that
would say for this type of request I'm
going to go look up the data that I need
from my database whether that's they
Tomic or whether it's a sequel database
or something like that then I reach a
handler function which just operates on
data so it gets a map in and it emits a
map out
this makes it incredibly easy to test
when I'm at the repple I can call my
handler function directly and just pass
it a map and look at the map that it
gives me back I don't need to mock
anything out I don't need to stub out
the database I don't need to have any
kind of fake o or M or in memory thing I
just call my handler so this this lets
me isolate things in a very nice way
what what I get back from the handler
then is another map that map will
typically have new values attached to it
that I want to transact back into the
database and so in pedestal that there
would be another function on our what we
call interceptors that's that's the same
as middleware really but it would be the
exit handler any briefly the thing with
what pedestal is yes sorry pedestal is a
web framework for server-side
applications created by cognate echt
it's it's pretty equivalent to ring but
allows some nice features for
server-sent events and asynchronous or
streaming responses so we've split the
call stack instead of just having you
know call down to the next layer of
middleware and then the return stream
coming up you can actually have
completely separate functions for for
enter and exit on requests but you can
do the same thing in ring middleware you
call the function below you bind the
return value to some name you can then
manipulate that do your side effecting
stuff that changes the database and then
return it upstream for further
conversion into HTML or again JSON or
XML or whatever else so we're in a
typical layered application we're sort
of drilling through all the layers and
once we've called into the domain the
domain calls into persistence and you
have this separation into service
classes and sort of domain concept
classes we would split that differently
and say the middleware calls persistence
then it calls my business logic or
domain
and then it calls persistence again
bracketing it rather than having it
drill through but as an ally DD scenario
your business logic is entirely
independent from your choice of
persistence mechanism or UI a framework
or whatever delivery mechanism it is
right it's the same the same key idea
that you have this thing that is that is
pure logic and not tied to anything else
yes I like to draw the domain as you
know the center of concentric rings or
or the middle of the hexagon rather than
the middle layer in a stack but don't
you lose something I mean if you have it
this way the way you described and I
think that's a perception many people
have is that it's really just data
that's put into some functions and then
there's new data coming out of it which
is of course what all computation is I'm
aware of that but it's really very
explicit because it's just data it's not
explicit it's not typed it's just as if
in Java you passed everything by means
of hash maps that include hashmaps that
include lists and in Java I would not
consider that a good Java design and I
would say well actually there's your in
Java or in having any other oo language
you are supposed to make your domain
language explicit by creating the
classes and methods and rule and the
relationships and whatever it is that
makes up your specific domain and make
give them names make them something that
has meaning within the language that's
not something you can do in an untyped
functional language right I dispute that
you can't do it but I agree that it's a
useful thing to do and let me unpack
that a little bit so one of the things
we always talk about is objects should
be able to maintain themselves in a
valid state it should be impossible to
put an object in you know to do an
operation on an object that renders it
inconsistent or nonsensical but very
often the notion of validity is context
dependent so I've often run into
situations where say I'm accepting data
from a user and and populating some
domain object I want to ask if it's
valid you
we put a validate method or an is valid
with a boolean return the problem is the
notion of validity for saving to the
database may be quite different than the
notion of validity for I don't know
ascending to a channel partner or
exporting an item I've done a lot of
Commerce work so I'll use an example
from there if I'm creating a new item in
the catalog I may need to give it just
the barest amount of information in
order to first save the item and it
should be valid to save even if it's not
valid to publish to the website so the
notion of validity is is very context
sensitive and we find that with almost
every operation that you want to do on
an object I think this is one of the
reasons that creating enterprise object
dictionaries is so hard for example so
much more often I find that I can create
a notion of conceptual integrity in good
function naming so you know this may
start to sound like I'm just recreating
Oh Oh as a naming convention but but I
get the functionality that I need by by
naming functions in my model that take
data in and give me back well-formed
data out but I can then use them a la
carte I'm not forced to use them all the
time the other way that that idea of
objects breaks down when you start using
it for your domain data is that
sometimes there are purely structural
manipulations I want to do that really
don't have any domain concept attached
to them so in link you can run a query
and then get a projection back of the
results or you know a sub select of the
columns and you know that that type we
don't name the type of the result that
you get back it's you know a set of
tuples because there's no domain concept
that says I only want these two fields
from all of these rows so if you've ever
had to create a
we object you know you want to display a
list of all the candidates before you
pick one and then get the detailed view
right you create a summary class and
then you have the real class and often
you know if you need business logic you
start duplicating it or you realize the
summary class exists only because I need
some set of named fields well you can
just do that with a data structure and
then again you get the the benefits of
all the built-in library of functions
okay so what you're saying is there is a
lot of there's a lot of functions that
just operate on these generic things and
you can use them as opposed to creating
specific stuff where you have to build
the stuff again right was the last point
yeah the the idiom or the the cloak
wheel saying is it's better to have a
hundred functions on one data structure
than ten functions that each operate on
one of ten data structures I actually
share that experience you mentioned
before the code becomes smaller all the
time once you work with it even though
to media typically happens when other
people look at my color code and how I
missed using one of those generic
functions and sort of my code shrinks
every time I talk to an expert who helps
me make it even smaller I think many
people have seen that this naive
approach of just creating a trying to
create a single object model breaks down
very quickly which is where you end up
with more complex object models with
validators and and I don't know other
pad classes that implement certain
patterns that just help you to
distribute all the functionality across
across the different concepts and to
isolate and decouple them and I can sort
of see the analogy to it just having a
set of a huge set of functions that
address the same aspect but what about
the typing aspect isn't the case that if
you are using an untyped language like
closure you have to do a lot of the type
checking that a that a statically typed
language will give you for free yourself
in your own code don't you spend most of
your time just catching type errors I
definitely encounter type errors don't
believe someone who says they don't they
just don't recognize them when they're
encountering them so for me a really
common error that I may
is I try to access a key from a map and
the key doesn't exist in that map well a
Haskell programmer will tell you that's
a type error and I agree it's a type
error I have I have used that map as if
it's something else
mm-hmm but I'm willing to make that
trade-off because I find that I'm
sufficiently more productive with those
type errors than I would be with making
the type system work for me the the
other aspect is there are certain types
that are represented and that I can ask
about and and do different things based
on the type but they're never concrete
types so I have predicates in closure
like you know is this a vector is this
sequential is this a collection is this
associative you know is it map like can
I access it via keys those are all
asking against interfaces and so you
know if I'm asking if something is a set
it may be a sorted set it may be a hash
set I don't really care and that's a
good guideline for any new types that
you would create so we've got a
construct enclosure called protocols I
haven't mentioned these yet because
they're kind of a more advanced topic
but this is probably an appropriate time
to bring them up a protocol is analogous
to a Java interface in that it's a
collection of signatures with no method
implementations in closure I can build
new types that reify those protocols or
that implement those protocols but I can
also add an extension to any existing
type and say how that existing type
supports this protocol and you can even
extend a protocol to nil and say how
does nil respond if I try and dispatch a
protocol to it which is a little bit of
an odd notion nil is not as immediately
deadly as null is in Java you know
danger put put yellow warning road signs
around that concept don't use it unless
you really really have a reason to so
when I have one of these protocols I
know that I have a
set of functions that I can dispatch to
any value that implements that protocol
and I can make a map implement a
protocol I can make a vector implement a
protocol what I usually find though is
that the protocols are very very narrow
and very specific so if you if you think
about the segregated interface idea
closure protocols tend to follow that
pretty carefully meaning I grouped
together a set of functions not based
around what the supplier knows that it
can do but based around what I want a
consumer to know about this thing mm-hmm
so for example one of the core
abstractions in closure is the notion of
sequence now this one's not a protocol
it's an interface but that's an
implementation detail at this point the
sequence simply means can I ask for the
next thing after the value that I've got
that's it that's that's the entirety of
the interface can I ask for next off of
this thing and there are many of the
core library functions that are written
around sequences so if you can convert
any value in your domain to act like a
sequence then you get the benefit of all
of those core functions if your value
also implements other protocols then you
can use it in other ways and so you can
think of these protocols as very narrow
projections to say their homomorphisms
to confined domains but they're very
narrow projections of behavior so that
seems similar to having lots of very
small interfaces in Java that just have
as few methods as possible and just
capture this one aspect of something yes
so that you end up with those classes
that have lots of little interfaces
influence collectable insertable and
whatever comparable whatever it is all
of those small little tiny things seems
like a very similar thing except that in
closure
you'd have to do that check yourself
before you call something right there is
nothing at compile time that'll prevent
you from from exerting an expectation
that's invalid right you have to somehow
know or check that these things are okay
because nothing checks for you
at Kampala that's correct nothing checks
at compile time building the Check Into
the receiving function is the typical
way of doing that and this isn't as
widely used as I think it should be but
every function can declare preconditions
in a sort of design by contract style so
you could attach a pre metadata to your
function that says you know there's this
must be a I don't know a line item in a
larger record or whatever so you do have
that option but yes it is something that
you would check for yourself okay again
it is a sacrifice that the compiler does
not catch certain types of errors for
you but I I'm comfortable making that
trade-off because I gain a lot via the
repple and basically you know not having
to pay attention to the compiler and all
the other situations mm-hm
typically it's me you as to justify
himself for liking dynamic typing it's
fun to do this to other for change do
you have any experience with with type
closure and if so can you tell us what
it is
I'll start by describing what it is type
closure is an effort to add via
libraries add typing to closure itself
type inferencing as well as type
checking and enforcement it's it's been
an ongoing project I've been watching it
with considerable interest but it's not
clear to me that it is even
theoretically possible to succeed
without constraining certain features of
closure itself and this this goes into
language theory that's not my forte so
I'm relying on opinions from other
experts who know what they're talking
about better than I do
I have only looked at it and dabbled
with it what I found was that it imposed
a pretty heavy compile time performance
penalty and the project where I was
looking at it is one where we needed to
compile interactively so we had to back
away from it pretty quickly I didn't
make a serious effort to to embed it
there is a similar project
called prismatic schema prismatic is a
company they do a like a social media or
social news aggregator and they're based
entirely in closure and they built this
schema library that lets you declare the
shape of the data that you want to work
with so instead of saying that my
functions are typed I'm saying that the
data is typed and I can declare the
structure with basically the the shape
of data structures is described via
other data structures that we know to
interpret as schemas I've used that
don't sleep good like XML schema in XML
well that may trigger some unfortunate
associations it's it's not as verbose or
painful is that no really if if I want
to say that some value should be a
vector of strings
I put bracket string as the schema
annotation on it so the bracket
indicates vector string is is actually
just a reference to the Java class
java.lang string so that's how I say
that this value needs to be a vector of
string then I have the option to apply
validation or not so it's common to turn
validations on when you're running tests
for example and then you can get
exceptions thrown if the values being
passed in don't match the schema and the
exceptions are actually quite nice
they're very precise in telling you
what's wrong with the the value that
you've passed in even if it's you know
three layers down in a nested map but
you don't have to incur that penalty all
the time so we can turn it off for
production code or we can actually just
call the validate function directly in
places where we need it so again one of
the one of the concepts that I really
like in the design of closure itself is
all these things that are bundled
together in other languages are sort of
pulled apart into their constituent
features and made optional and a la
carte does that extend to the library
ecosystem
to the library verses framework debates
is it more that closure does libraries
where other languages do frameworks or
is it that's just a core language kind
of thing I think there's a community
style that says we should favor small
composable libraries over frameworks
that that started quite early in the
closure realm and has continued even as
the community of users has grown by a
factor of a hundred I don't see anything
acting to change that Tour de France for
frameworks but I will say the libraries
are not always as composable or as
plug-and-play
as as the aspirations would indicate you
mentioned the growth in the number of
users are there other well-known
examples of closer users other than
prismatic can you name a few I can't
name a few actually probably the the
largest company that I could name that
has adopted closure in any significant
way is Walmart they started last year
with a program to capture receipts from
every point of sale terminal in every
store it might be kind of surprising
that they weren't doing this before but
the data pathway was very long and
tortuous to get into a warehouse and
then into data Mart's and then out so
they're actually capturing data as it's
being sent to the receipt printer REE
parsing it to build this database of
what they call a receipts the first
application they built on top of that
was something called savings catcher
that was built in closure and rolled out
and part of national and maybe
international advertising campaigns
savings catcher means if you have missed
out on a coupon or a competitive deal or
something like that then right at the
point-of-sale you will get an instant
discount for it and that was built
largely using closure for the data
aggregation
and plumbing and roll up across all of
those 5,000 some odd stores how does one
manage to to sneak something like
closure into such an environment
I mean Walmart well maybe not this we
don't have to talk about this specific
example I don't know how much you know
about it but the in just in general
what's your experience do you have to
have a scenario where but climbed or the
MANET management just doesn't care or it
can actively convince decision makers
that it's a good idea to bet on this
rather unknown language I've found an
incredible mix across the environment
over the last couple of years it turns
out that there are a lot of closeted
lisp enthusiasts uh-huh and many of them
have been around long enough that
they're in senior positions and so those
are the those are the very easy ones to
convince they saw the parens years ago
and fell into the the blue void of Lisp
others I would say because I work for
cognate X a lot of clients come to us
already interested in closure but I've
had some other conversations a very
common pathway to get closure in to an
environment is via non production code
particularly tests or automation of some
kind
and because closure is very nice for
working with data you can use it to
handle a lot of you know internal data
processing chores and get things done
quickly and gain attention that way in
terms of getting into production
there was an idea a couple of years ago
that said well it's just a jar file so
as long as it's running on the JVM
nobody really needs to know and you can
just slip it in I don't necessarily
consider that a very team-oriented
perspective or or a healthy way to to
deal with your organization but I would
say you know being open and transparent
about bringing it in and describing the
advantages and then being ready to back
it up with assistance
and this this is a crucial part if
you're gonna be the the champion for
bringing a language into your company
you need to be available to people to
help them solve their problems because
oftentimes when they come at you with a
problem 50% of the approach they take is
about the problem and and their
inability to solve it and 50% is a you
know either a veiled accusation that it
was a bad idea or maybe maybe you you
perceive it as a veiled accusation that
it never should have been brought in so
you you know you you have to be prepared
for that how much of a burden do you
think the aleef of future generations
when you build something closer is it
will it be easy for for somebody to pick
up or how good you feel about do this
doing this how how confident are you
that it's gonna stick around for the
long term maybe that's the wrong
question to ask but I'm still interested
in your answer sure at this point
closure is six years old I think so so
it's already been around for a while and
it doesn't show signs of withering in
fact the community's growing
year-over-year but I will also say you
know we need to consider the the
shelf-life of applications in the
context of your company if you're a
startup or if you're in the web space
you know there's no point in building
something that you expect to last for
five years nothing's going to last five
years in your startup so you're already
prepared I hope to throw everything away
and rewrite it multiple times in a
larger Enterprise here we risk veering
into the territory I spend most of my
time talking about it in a larger
enterprise you do have to be concerned
about time spans like five years ten
years and so on and so you know good
architecture comes into play I hope that
you're building your systems in such a
way that different pieces can be
replaced at different rates and at
different times and this would be like
everything else you know it's it's
another box with an implementation
inside the box and it may get replaced
it's just the nature of things
I'll say another one of those sort of
toxic ideas is when somebody comes in
and says well this stuff is is okay for
me but my colleagues would never
understand it and so you know first I
have to replace everyone else in my
company but me or something like that
it's simply not true there there's no
magic to this Lisp is not inaccessible
to mere mortals the the parentheses do
in fact disappear and you quickly see
the structure of the code and having the
repple there is an amazing learning tool
you know it's like going back to the
8-bit days when you boot it up into
basic and you can just you know do stuff
immediately and see what happens so
people can learn it pretty quickly I'm
not I'm not worried at all about leaving
something unmaintainable behind okay one
of the things that I've always liked
about a closure community is that there
are so many great things to learn from
so many talks and books and online
resources and stuff like that what are
your favorite recommendations where
would you point people to who want to
find out more about the language and the
ecosystem there are a ton of talks on
YouTube now from several years worth of
conferences so you could spend days just
watching videos on amazing and cool
things people have done closure TV is
the the channel there I also think we've
got some excellent books the the sort of
first round of tutorial books are now
out of the way and we're starting to get
books on ok what do you do for day two
and and how do I live with this long
term one of them is called living
closure by Karen Mayer and another one
that I think is in early access now but
will probably be final by the time this
airs is closure applied by Alex Miller
and Ben Vandegrift I think those are
both excellent books for learning how to
do things that are going to last for
some period of time and learning how a
real project goes beyond just learning
the language
okay good we'll put all of those all
those resources as well as other things
we mentioned into the show notes do you
have any parting last words to future
enclosure users one more thing that I
would mention that that I haven't done
before
Java interrupts from closure and
JavaScript interrupt from closure script
were both made incredibly simple for a
reason there's a strong temptation when
adopting a new language to rebuild
everything in that language but you're
on the JVM with all the billions of
dollars that have been invested in
software there so embrace that and go
ahead and use the libraries and use the
the core that's already there don't
reinvent the wheel it's a waste of time
and money okay Mike it's been a pleasure
having you on the show I enjoyed this
very very much thanks a lot for for
spending your time with us thank you
happy to be here thanks for listening to
se radio an educational program brought
to you by I Triple E software magazine
for more information about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website at SE - radioman to provide
feedback you can write comments on each
episode on the website or read review on
itunes mention a message us on twitter @
se radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google
you can also email us at team at SES
radio net this and all other episodes of
SU radio is licensed under the Creative
Commons 2.5 license thanks again for
your support
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]